<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects on Luca Garbi</title>
    <link>http://lucagarbi.space/project/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Projects on Luca Garbi</description>
    <generator>Source Themes academia (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 20 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="http://lucagarbi.space/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Single photon source based on IFWM</title>
      <link>http://lucagarbi.space/project/bachelor-thesis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lucagarbi.space/project/bachelor-thesis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This project was conceived as the final project of my Bachelor&amp;rsquo;s studies at the Department of Physics of the University of Trento. The downloadable files are the thesis itself, the LaTex template and also the presentation used for the discussion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Integrated single photon sources are key building blocks for on-chip quantum computation, quantum information and quantum technologies in general.
Single photon states can be produced through a heralding process between correlated photon pairs generated via nonlinear optical processes. On-chip heralded single photon sources based on spontaneous four wave mixing have been
already demonstrated. The purpose of this thesis is to show the advantages and
potentialities of intermodal four wave mixing in the single photon generation
framework. The photon source is developed on a silicon chip, the ideal platform for integrated nonlinear processes and scalable quantum devices, thanks
also to its mature and cheap fabrication technology. A heralded single photon
source based on a IFWM process in silicon waveguides is here demonstrated.
In the first chapter the basics of the formation and propagation of waveguide
modes are given, with a focus on optical multimode waveguides. Nonlinear
optics is then introduced with a concise overview of the main second and third
order nonlinear processes. A particular attention is paid to spontaneous four
wave mixing and its inefficiencies in view of a single photon source application. Through this process, in fact, the signal and idler photons are generated
close to the wavelength of the pump, thus limiting the generation spectrum.
Moreover, narrow spectral post filtering is used to increase the spectral purity,
limiting the brightness and the integration of these type of sources. Intermodal
four wave mixing can be used to remove the need of tight spectral filtering and
to achieve broad band quantum light generation, from the near to the mid infrared.
The second chapter initially introduce some elements of photon statistics and
deals with the basics of probabilistic single photon sources. A close attention is
paid to heralded single photon sources and the experimental metrics necessary
in order to characterize their performance. The last part of chapter 2 presents a
heralded single photon source based on intermodal FWM on a SOI multimode
waveguide. A description of the chip used, which has been fabricated by the
Centre for Materials and Microsystems of Bruno Kessler Foundation (Trento,
Italy), is initially provided. Next, the experimental set-up for the source characterization is described. The measurements have been carried out by dr. Stefano
Signorini and Matteo Sanna (master student) in the Nanoscience Laboratory,
in the Department of Physics of the University of Trento.
The analysis I carried out on the measurements is presented in the last chapter
of this thesis. The experimental demonstration of a silicon integrated source
of heralded single photons is reported. The source exploits the intermodal
four wave mixing to generate the heralding idler in the near infrared and the
heralded signal in the mid infrared.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Swinging Atwood&#39;s machine</title>
      <link>http://lucagarbi.space/project/sam-sam/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lucagarbi.space/project/sam-sam/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This project was conceived in the context of an honour program (PAF) at the Department of Physics of the University of Trento during the fall semester of 2018. It has later been modified, corrected and translated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Swinging Atwood’s machine is a system similar to the Atwood’s pulley, except
for the degrees of freedom of one of its two masses. Indeed it can swing in a bidimensional plane, producing a system that - for some values of parameters and initial conditions - turns out to be chaotic. This machine consists of two masses connected by an inextensible and massless rope, that can move on two
radiusless and massless pulleys. Moreover the two masses can not collide.
The study of the Swinging Atwood&amp;rsquo;s machine dynamics is made with Lagrangian mechanics.
Numerical and graphical simulations of the chaotic system are made and the Lyapunov&amp;rsquo;s exponent is calculated for a thousand values of mass ratio.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MC &amp; QMC methods in Finance</title>
      <link>http://lucagarbi.space/project/mc-qmc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lucagarbi.space/project/mc-qmc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this work - currently only in Italian - Monte Carlo and Quasi-Monte Carlo methods are used in order to find the fair-value of derivative instruments, whose dynamic is given by the financial model of Black-Scholes-Merton. In particular, in the first part is present a MC alternative to the finite difference method in order to solve the Black-Scholes PDE. In the second part, instead, a comparison is made between Monte Carlo and Quasi-Monte Carlo when dealing with the Asian options pricing problem.
Both codes, in C language, are present in Appendix.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Index Futures Strategies Library</title>
      <link>http://lucagarbi.space/project/trading-strat/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lucagarbi.space/project/trading-strat/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My earliest attempt at active investing, carried out during the summer-break of my second year of Bachelor&amp;rsquo;s studies in physics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used the MetaTrader environment (mainly exploiting the MQL5 language, which is free and based on C++) for developing algorithmic trading strategies based on technical analysis, in particular price patterns. The strategies were subsequently back-tested for some in-sample data and optimized using parametric sweeps and genetic algorithms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some (out-of-sample) profitable systems went live, but there has been no further development, nor creation of new systems since. This is mainly due to the resumption of the studies, plus the quick realization that the combined effects of high fees, slippage and data quality (all factors limited by my capital at the time) were not able to surpass traditional passive investing returns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the attachment are present a couple of simple trading strategies, plus a sample of the pattern library I used for futures on indices (mainly DAX and FTMIB).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ELETTRA Synchrotron Simulation</title>
      <link>http://lucagarbi.space/project/elettra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lucagarbi.space/project/elettra/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This project was conceived in the context of an honour program (PAF) at the Department of Physics of the University of Trento during the spring semester of 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The initial aim was to create the more accurate simulation possible of the ELETTRA synchrotron in Trieste, Italy. The code was initially written in MATLAB, then in Python. This was the result obtained at the end of the semester, when the project on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://lucagarbi.space/project/sam-sam/&#34; title=&#34;Swinging Attwood&#39;s Machine&#34;&gt;Swinging Attwood&amp;rsquo;s Machine&lt;/a&gt; started.
I do not dispose of the proper documentation and a clean code like in that case, but plan to write it in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modelling phototransduction and other biochemical networks</title>
      <link>http://lucagarbi.space/project/winter-school/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lucagarbi.space/project/winter-school/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This report is based on the hands-on session, given at the University of Trento by Prof. Daniele Dell’Orco, on January 29th, 2020, in the context of the Winter School on Physics of the Cell. The objective of this write-up is on one hand to briefly synthesize the lecture on the modelling of dynamic biophysical systems, on the other hand to implement a simplified model of phototransduction via the ODEbased version of IQMtools, i.e. a MATLAB toolbox used in class for the implementation of a different biophysical system.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
